<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[iLee]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[I write code that sounds awesome and music that's bug free]]></subtitle>
  <link href="http://ilee.co.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ilee.co.uk"/>
  <updated>2013-08-06T17:04:47.341Z</updated>
  <id>http://ilee.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lee Crossley]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[leee@hotmail.co.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static Site Generators]]></title>
    <link href="http://ilee.co.uk/static-site-generators/"/>
    <id>http://ilee.co.uk/static-site-generators/</id>
    <published>2013-08-06T16:15:06.000Z</published>
    <updated>2013-08-06T17:04:43.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>You may not have noticed but static HTML is taking back the web.</strong></p>
<p>We all thought the days of static HTML websites were long gone when almighty server-side content management systems developed. With their powerful  architecture and databases, often requiring licence fees and a few dedicated GB of RAM on your web server, why wouldn&#39;t bigger be better? It turns out it&#39;s not.</p>
<p><em>We</em> got it wrong.</p>
<ul>
<li>Static HTML files are fast, no need for in-memory caching.</li>
<li>Static HTML files are secure, there&#39;s much less to try to hack.</li>
<li>Static HTML files <strong>JUST WORK</strong> on virtually any hosting environment.</li>
</ul>
<p>OK, so what are we supposed to do, go back to coding like it&#39;s 1995? Managing common HTML between pages, sitemaps and &quot;last updated&quot; dates manually? Forgetting about new shiny technology like SASS and LESS, JADE and HAML? Not quite. </p>
<p><strong>Enter the Static Site Generator.</strong></p>
<p>A Static Site Generator is a program which generates and outputs static HTML. The idea is that all the hard work is done upfront, so the user doesn&#39;t have to do the waiting. Think of it as <em>extreme caching</em> :)</p>
<p>Many generators already exist for personal sites, blogs and reference sites etc, and are available for pretty much every language/platform you can imagine. You don&#39;t have to use one off the shelf, they&#39;re pretty easy to put together (hence there being quite a few). It&#39;s also easy to get it working exactly how is best for you and your specific project.</p>
<p>I wrote a bespoke static site generator for a client earlier this year, which ingested a source atom feed and translated the data to HTML5 and RDFa using C# (wasn&#39;t my language of choice but I was constrained by internal politics, I was just happy to get the static site generator approved).</p>
<p>As a final point, this blog is static HTML. It&#39;s hosted for free on <a href="https://github.com/leecrossley/leecrossley.github.io">github</a> pages, with a custom domain name. I&#39;m writing markdown right now and using node.js to generate the HTML and CSS. Hopefully you didn&#39;t notice the page loading.</p>
]]></content>
    <category scheme="http://ilee.co.uk/tags/web/" term="web"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
